Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 8 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 December-1786 Mss.B.F85inventory08
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 8 -- Letters to Franklin
1783 December-1786
Mss.B.F85inventory08
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
1,204 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Nairne, Edward. London
    Scope and Contents note
    A hygrometer on a new construction; M. de Luc's hygrometer. Death of Mrs. Clark's only brother. Mrs. Nairne, Polly and Fanny not a little flattered at Franklin's mentioning them.
    Bibliography
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks, VI, 449).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning Mr. [Thomas] Barclay's demand for all public accounts to be lodged at the consular Office.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 3; L. in 3d P. 2p.; Jackson, William
    Regretting his departure for England, as it will delay his meeting with Franklin. Mr. [Richard] Bache and his family in perfect health when he left Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Newenham, Sir Edward
    Concerning politics in Ireland; the action of the Volunteers; description of their Assembly; acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 16th ult., relative to the Commerical Treaty not yet being concluded; is sick of Ireland and the way she is controlled by England. Col. Grattan's failure to be elected Colonel of the Dublin Independents; fears his opposition in the Reform Bill.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.] December 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Guyon, -----
    Obliged to have recourse again to Franklin's generosity in his present unfortunate situation.
    (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 4; L.S. 2p.; Lenoir, Jean-Charles-Pierre. Paris
    Mentions the engraving of Franklin's stove sent by him to M. Cadet de Vaux. M. Cadet hopes Franklin will superintend the construction of a stove which is being built, according to his principles. Begs Franklin to send him a description of the stove and also of the grate which he intends to have built for open fires; wishes to make both public; debt the Government will owe Franklin as they are now busy perfecting the means of substituting coal for wood.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Rocheplate,-----, de
    Begs for an audience.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1784 December 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Mariamne Alexander
    Arranging to dine with Franklin and spend the night with Mme. Helvétius. Hoped they would see him at St. Germain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 8; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Cadet de Vaux, Antoine-Alexis
    Sending a letter from Lieutenant-General of Police and two tickets from Messrs. Le Grand and Molinos.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Rocheplate, ----- de
    Franklin's letter appointing a day and hour never reached him until too late to keep the appointment; begs him to name another time.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 9; A.L.S. 5p.; Banks, Sir Joseph. London
    Balloons, Experiment of M. [Jacques Alexandre César] Charles. Practical flying belongs to France; theoretical flying to England; cites Bishop Wilkins and Mr. [Henry] Cavendish, Mr. Mitchell's paper on light being subject to gravitation. Description of a miserable comet noted by Mr. Nathan[iel] Pigot[t] in his observatory at Yorkshire. Account of a piece of mechanism consisting of four wings and warranted to fly.
    Printed, almost entire, in Hale's Franklin in France, II, 276.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 9; L.S. 4p.; Osmont, -----, chevalier d'
    Begging for news of Jacques Charles d'Osmont, who at one time settled at Petersburg, Va.; rumors of his death; begs Franklin to ascertain the truth of this report; the great importance to him of this information.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 10; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Pio, Luigi de
    Sending Franklin the fourth volume of M. Filangieri's work together with his letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Vebon, J
    Sending a letter entrusted to him by Dr. [Samuel] Cooper, and also some Boston papers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Vermonnet, Jean-Baptiste-Arthur. St. Domingo
    Reminding Franklin of his former request for the position of Vice-Consul in one of the three departments of the United States. Account of the financial troubles which obliged him to make this request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 December 12; 1784 Jan. 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Rivault, Bouttrel du
    His services in the American army; one of his legs badly injured during the war; complains of the ungracious treatment he received, the lack of clothes, provisions and pay; applies to Franklin to enable him to obtain his just dues.
    (In French. In dupilcate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 December 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Girault de Keroudou, -----, abbé
    In the collection of President Rolland which he sent Franklin, he will find a dissertation on the use of the French language in inscriptions, treaties, etc.; the author wishes to make some changes and additions on the subject and desires to know if the Resolutions of the Republic and some of their inscriptions are in French.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 December 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Menier de Saint Yver, -----.
    Reminds Franklin of his promise to engage Mr. [Thomas] Barclay on his return to aid Mr. [J.] Schaffer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 December 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Febvre, -----. Lille
    Sends a copy of the proceedings in which is inserted his speech for the publication of peace.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 December 15; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Sorin de Bonne, Madame -----
    Begging Franklin to procure her a copy of the treaty of the United States with England and one of their treaty with Spain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1783 December 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Beauregard, ----- de
    Is the Vice-Consul of Sardinia at the French port of Cette; advantage of having an American Consul stationed at that port; offers his services.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1783 December 16; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Williamos, Charles
    Asking for the necessary passports for America; proposes to set off in two days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Lamardelle, ----- de
    Asking for Mr. [Thomas] Barclay's address; hears that he is Agent for Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 18; Engraved N. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Invitation for dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Courtette, -----, baron de
    Is a brother Mason; objectly wretched, desiring only to die; is the father of four children—a girl, whom he has placed in a convent, and three boys, all at military schools; begs Franklin to render him some assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Rocheplate, ----- de
    Sending Franklin two manuscripts on geometry; hopes they will amuse and interest him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Tonnelier, Madame. Moulins
    Her husband, a fellow-countryman of Franklin; account for his work, death, and her present unfortunate situation with a large family to bring up and educate; begs Franklin to procure her a continuation of certain priviledges, or a pension from the King.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 19; L. in 3d P. 2p.; Sargent, John and Rosamund Chambers
    If Franklin intends coming to London in the ensuing spring or summer, they beg his acceptance of their town house, which with their country house and equipage are all at his service. Health of his family. Their great desire to see Franklin; will be ashamed to talk with him of England and its Government, which daily sinks deeper in disgrace.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Barney, Capt Joshua. Havre-de-Grace
    Has shipped the three barrels and the box of seeds on a vessel for Rouen; has none of the nuts of which Franklin spoke, but will bring a quantity on his next voyage. Thanks him for his kind offer which the shortness of his stay prevents his accepting.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 19; A.L.S. 4p.; Bonnefoy, ---------. Lyons
    Is a member of the College of Surgery at Lyons; desires to lay before Franklin a plan, which, if carried out, would bring American surgery to the last degree of perfection; his friendshiip with various French surgeons of note; if Franklin approves his suggestion, will send him the details of the plan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 19; A.L.S 4p.; Estko, Anne d'
    When her brother, Thaddeus Kosciuszko, entered the service of the United States, he left with her the direction of his property and lands; no word has come from him since his departure; on account of his reported death, the creditors of her eldest brother wish to seize his estate; in this emergency, begs Franklin to obtain some certified information of his existence or death; encloses an extract from a letter of M. lc Comte de Murinet which ought to be suffcient in itself to prove her brother's existence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaudreuil, Louis-Philippe Rigaud, marquis de
    On the 3d ult., sent Franklin two memoirs entrusted to his care by M. Pacaud, asking for the position of American Consul in St. Domingo; begs Franklin to send the memoirs to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Hardy, -------. Ervy
    Ignorant what is the dominant religion in America or whether Congress intends having an exclusive religion. Is a Roman Catholic priest, Principal of the College of Ervy-le-Châtel; offers to expatriate himself for good of his religion and the service of the Americans; hopes Congress will be able to place him in an advantageous position thinks he could persuade several of his friends to accompany him, if the prospect appeared hopeful.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 20; N. in 3d p. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Paris
    Accepting his invitation for dinner on the 25th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Chase, Samuel. London
    Before this reaches Franklin he will hear of the dismission of the late Ministry; Mr. [William] pitt is Prime Minister; no other appointment is fixed; names of some who are expected to hold office.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Barney, Capt Joshua. Havre-de-Grace
    Among the packages brought on shore, is one directed to Franklin containing snuff and tabacco; would have been heavily fined if he had been detected bringing it ashore; supposes Franklin has letters concerning it; as it cannnot be sent, begs for Franklin's instructions on that head.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 22; L.S. 2p.; Bariatinskoy, Prince Ivan Sergeevich. Paris
    Concerning a Resolution of Congress to obtain the king's permission, in order that the French officers who served in America might accept the insignia of an order to be established in memory of the Revolution; informed that the Royal consent has been obtained; desires Franklin to send him the details of the affair that he may make them known to his court.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 22; L.S. 2p.; Bariatinskoy, Prince Ivan Sergeevich. Paris
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Giraud, ------. Paris
    The United States, having had a large share in the dedication of this almanac, takes great pleasure in sending them a copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 22; L. in 3d P. 1p.; The Ambassador of the Emperor of Austria
    Requesting him to forward letters to Baron de Beelen, the other to one Professor Maätter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 22; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Valnais, Joseph de and Madame -----
    Will wait on him the following Thursday. Acknowledge Mr. [William Temple] Franklin's kindness in sending Dr. [Samuel] Cooper's letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 23; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan. Paris
    Will dine with Franklin on Thursday. Encloses the letter of M. de Vergennes relative to the 22d Article of the Preliminary Treaty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 23; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Mayo, Joseph. Paris, Hotel de Portugal
    Owing to his late illness, is unable to dine with Dr. Franklin on Thursday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 23; L.S. 1p.; Lasson, ----- de
    Requesting Franklin's presence at the opening of his shop; all his wares made of straw.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 23; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Harrison, -----. Paris
    Prevented from accepting Franklin's invitation by an indisposition which has kept him confined since his arrival in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Creuzé, -----
    Certain reflections on the construction of ac¯rostatic machines; if these ideas can be of any use, presents them to Franklin as a slight mark of his respect.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Lamy, -----. Paris
    Sent to him and to the Comte d'Estaing a pamphlet he wrote on the Chevalier d'Assas and the regiment of Auvergne, part of which served under the eyes of Gen. Washington; fears the copy never reached him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 26; L.S. 1p.; Breteuil, Louis-Auguste Le Tonnelier, baron de
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter, 1 in which he asks that [J.] Schaffer should be sent to the Islands; will do all he can, but gives certain reasons why it may be legally impossible.
    General note
    1 Draft of this letter in French (XXX, 154a), setting forth M. Schaffer's respectable connections in America and Franklin's reasons for making this request. [1 p.].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Jay, John. Bath
    His indisposition. Acknowledgment of Franklin's kindness. Report of Franklin's illness. Declines writing about politics; opinions in England for and against Franklin.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 47; Bigelow, VIII, 403).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Greene, Griffin. Paris
    Begging Franklin to send the enclosed letter for General [Nathanael] Greene, by the first vessel for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Gérard de Rayneval, Joseph-Mathias.
    Recommending the enclosed packet to Franklin's care. One of his friends, M. Chateaufort, desires a letter of recommendation to Dr. [Richard] Price; he expects to spend several months in England from motives of curiosity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 27; A.L.S. 7p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. Clausthall
    Acknowledging Franklin's Kindness to him in Paris. Begs for some details of M. [Jacques Alexandre César] Charles's experiment in aerial navigation; his serious reasons for desiring this information. Description and drawing of the Weisner, an isolated mountain in the country of Hessia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 28; L. in 3d P. 2p.; Charretié John
    Announcing his hurried departure for London; sends the enclosed by a messenger and if Franklin has any commands for Mr. [John] Sargent or any other person, begs they may be sent at once.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 29.; A.L.S. 2p.; Walter, John. London
    Concerning a late improvement which consists of printing with entire words instead of single letters; its gracious reception in England; if it would be equally acceptable to America, will send an exact copy of the founts and the mode of conducting it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 30.; L.S. 2p.; Van Moorsel, Theodoor, & Co.
    Offering several cannon, the purchase of which might prove serviceable to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783? December 30.; A.L.S. 2p.; Du Ponceau, Jean-Michel, chevalier
    Uneasiness concerning his brother [Peter Stephen]'s fate, has not heard from him for a year; encloses a letter for him and begs for some information regarding his whereabouts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 31.; A.L.S. 3p.; Holker, Jean. Rouen
    Acknowledging Franklin's kind letter by M. Lamot and reminding him of his promise to visit them before he leaves the country. Franklin having attained all he longed and wished for, it is high time he enjoyed himself. The wheels are found and will be forwarded as soon as the river is navigable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 31.; A.L.S. 1p.; Dubuysson des Aix, Charles-François, chevalier
    The Marquis de la Fayette desires the papers which the writer sent Franklin, in order to find out if he is eligible to the Society of the Cincinnati; begs Franklin to forward them to the Marquis, and to grant him favorable consideration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 31.; L.S. 1p.; Breteuil, Louis-Auguste Le Tonnelier, baron de.
    Since his last letter, has ascertained that [John] Schaffer has been found guilty of swindling and transferred to the prison of the Conciergerie; under these circumstances, cannot possibly interfere; advises Franklin to apply to the Keeper of the Seals for a pardon or a commutation of his punishment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 December 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Wishes for the New Year. Sees by the papers that it is proposed to build a city and a palace for Congress; if his feeble talents can be of any use, hopes Franklin will not forget him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783. December.]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Carter, John
    Requests him to forward a letter by the express he sends to Capt. [Joshua] Barney at Havre.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 2p.; Bachelier, Jean Jacques
    Proposes to establish a technical school in the United States for training the young in useful arts and industries.
    (In French. In Franklin's handwriting.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1783; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Berthier fils, -----
    Asking a letter of recommendation from Franklin. Is going to establish himself in business at Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bingham, William
    Asks for a passport, and the letter which was promised him for the Count d'Adhémar.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783; A.L.S. 1p.; Blanchard, François. Paris?
    Informed by M. de Sarsfield that Franklin intends coming to see his flying ship, the following day; the mechanism at present entirely concealed; begs him to postpone his visit for several days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783]; A.L.S. 2p.; Bourdic, Baronne de
    Preserves with the greatest care the medal given her by Franklin; another precious possession is the little picture of Franklin drawn by Mlle. de Givonne; quotes the verses written underneath, composed by herself. Begging Franklin to grant a brief audience to two of her friends, Abbé de la Mailière and his father, the General.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1783; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bourdic, Baronne de
    Will bid good-bye to Dr. Franklin at Passy. Asks leave to introduce some ladies to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 2p.; Bourdic, Baronne de
    Requesting Dr. Franklin to give a letter of recommendation to one of her friends from Languedoc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; Extract from L. 2p.; Bowdoin, James
    Concerning the inhabitants of Falmouth in Casco Bay, who, in October, 1775, had the greater part of their houses and effects destroyed by the merciless orders of Admiral Graves; opportunity presented of befriending these people.
    (Copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1783; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Brancas, Count and Countess de
    Inviting Franklin and his grandson to dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; A.L.S. 2p.; Brandenstein, Frédéric Guillaume de
    Writes from near Bayreuth asking for information about the United States, and if colonists would be accepted and under what conditions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.] Monday, 3rd; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Has arranged to go to the Salon with Franklin and take breakfast at M. Vernet's. Will give him particulars when he calls at her house on Wednesday evening.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.] Sunday evening; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Will await Franklin Monday morning to go to see the paintings and then take breakfast at M. Vernet's.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?] Saturday; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Hopes Franklin will come and take tea at her house that afternoon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Asking Franklin to take tea and bring his son [William Temple Franklin] and Benjamin [Franklin Bache].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Sorry to hear that Franklin and his grandson have company at their house on Christmas day and cannot dine with her. Hopes Franklin will call in the evening to take tea and hear some music.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Cambray, Col
    Is extremely sorry that he cnnot have the honor of accepting his invitation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Carmichael, William, d. 1795
    Introducing a member of the Marquis d'Aranda's family, Dr. Simon de Casas.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Carter, Mrs. John
    Will call on Dr. Franklin accompanied by the young gentlemen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Carter, Mr and Mrs John
    Invite him to dine with them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; Mem. 2p.; de Castillon, Le Blanc
    Recommends Prosper Mouret, a printer, who wishes to go to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Chester, André
    Secretary of Admiralty and interpreter of English at Marseilles, asks to be authorized to attend to American shipping interests.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; L. in 3d P. 3p.; Duchesac, -----, and Franché de Cleairval
    Are theatrical directors; propose to establish a theatre at Philadelphia and bring over a troupe of actors from France; ask Franklin's approval and support.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Cologan, Mme de
    Requests a letter of introduction for Mr. John Shaw, a merchant who is going to Teneriffe for a cargo of wines which he will take from there to Philadelphia and other ports.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783?]; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Cologan, Mme de
    Bidding good-bye to Franklin on her departure from Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783?] Tuesday; A.L.S. 1p.; Crèvecoeur, St. Jean de
    Desiring to know where he can procure two of Franklin's medals; imprudently promised them in Normandy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Cussac, -----. Paris
    Sending a prospectus of a new edition of Plutarch's works. dedicated to the Marquis de la Fayette; begs Franklin's interest on behalf of the work both in France and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783]; Verses. 1p.; D-----, N---- A----, abbé
    Inscription for the pedestal of an obelisk to be erected to Liberty on a square in Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Delavoiepierre, -----. Paris
    Proposes to go to the United States to make wine. Offers to submit his process and methods to doctors and chemists, if Franklin approves of his plans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783]; A.L.S. 1p.; Deux-Ponts, Marianne Camasse, duchesse La douairière de
    Begging Franklin and his grandson to spend Easter with her, as well as Keralio, Caillot and [de] Fontenet; they will all drink tea and play chess.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Deux-Ponts, Marianne Camasse, duchesse La douairière de
    Sends him some new leaves to read. Asks him to return those he has read and to observe the strictest secrecy about them. Will return to Versailles soon to await the home-coming of her son whose arrival is expected in the beginning of June.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [After 1777 June 3]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; D'honne, Mrs